现在我们理解了DES的工作过程，我们来看几个针对DES的攻击
Now that we understand how DES works, let's look at a few attacks on DES,
我们从穷举攻击开始
and we're going to start with an attack called exhaustive search.
我们的目标是，给定一些输入、输出对(mi, ci)
So our goal here is basically that given a few input-output pairs, (mi, ci),
我们的目标是找出完成这些映射的密钥
our goal is to find the key that maps these m's to the c's.
换句话说，我们的目标是找出密钥，
将m1, m2, m3 映射成 c1, c2, c3
In other words, our goal is to find the key that maps m1, m2, m3 into c1, c2, c3,
如我所说，找出能完成这个映射的密钥
and as I said, our goal is to find the key that does this mapping.
第一个问题是，我们怎么知道这个密钥是唯一的？
The first question is, how do we know that this key is unique?
于是，我们简单分析一下
And so, let's do a little bit of analysis to show that in fact
事实上一个输入输出对就完全限制住一个DES密钥了
just one pair is enough to completely constrain a DES key,
所以这个问题说得通
and that's why this question makes sense.
我们看，如何证明这个简单的引理
OK, so let's see. So we're going to prove this simple lemma.
我们假设DES是一个理想的密码
Now let's assume that DES is what's called an ideal cipher.
什么是理想的密码？我们要假定
So what is an ideal cipher? Basically we're going to pretend like DES is made up of
DES是由一些随机可逆函数组成。换句话说，
对每一个密钥，DES都实现了一个随机可逆函数
random invertible functions. In other words,
for every key, DES implements a random invertible function.
由于DES有2的56次方个可能密钥，我们假定
Since there are 2^56 keys in DES, we're going to pretend like DES really is a collection
DES是2的56次方个函数的集合，它们在64位字符串上可逆
of 2^56 functions that are invertible from ｛0,1｝^64 to ｛0,1｝^64. OK? So of course,
当然，DES并非2的56次方个随机函数的集合，但是我们这里理想化了
DES is not a collection of 2^56 random functions, but we can idealize about the cipher and pretend
先假设DES是这么一个集合。那我们能得到什么？
that it is such a collection. Then what can we say?
事实上，给定一对明文和密文
Then in fact it turns out that just given one message and ciphertext, you just give me
给我一对明文和密文，只有一个密钥可以将这个明文映射成这个密文
one pair, message and ciphertext, there's already only one key that maps this message to that ciphertext.
只给定一对m和c，我可以让你找到把m映射到c的密钥
So already just given one pair m and c, I can ask you, find me the key that maps m to c,
并且这个答案还是唯一的。事实上，答案唯一的概率是99.5%
and the solution is very likely to be unique. In fact it's going to be unique with probability roughly 99.5%.
我应当说这个命题是正确的，对所有m和c而言，而这个概率
I should say that this statement is true for all m and c, and the probability is just over the choice
与组成密码的随机置换有关
of the random permutations that make up the cipher.
我们写这个证明。证明是直接的。我们问
So let's write a proof. This is fairly straightforward. So what we're basically asking is,
存在另一个不同于k的密钥，满足。。
what's the probability that there exists some key that's not equal to k such that,
我们知道根据定义c等于DES(k, m)，但我们问
well, c we know is equal to DES(k, m) by defintion of c and m, but we're asking how likely is it
存在另一密钥k'也满足这一等式的可能性是多少？
that there's this other key, k-prime, that also satisfies this equality?
可以发现如果这是对的，如果这样的密钥k'存在，那么给定m和c
You realize that if this is true, if such a key k-prime exists, then just given m and c,
你还不能确定正确的密钥是k还是k'，因为两个密钥都能正确工作，对吧？
you can't decide whether the right key is k or k-prime, because both of them work. OK?
我想证明这个发生的概率很小
But I want to argue that this happens with low probability.
存在密钥k’满足这个关系，是什么意思？
Well, so what does it mean that there exists a key k-prime that satisfies this relation?
第一个密钥，全是0的密钥，满足这个等式的概率是多少？
Well, we're asking, what's the probability that the first key, the all-zero key, satisfies it?
或者是第二个密钥满足之。或者是第三个密钥，等等
Or, the second key satisfies it. Or, the third key satisfies it. And so on and so forth.
根据概率的并集上界，我们可以计算所有密钥k'的和的概率上界
So by the union bound, we can bound this probability by the sum over all keys k-prime,
对于所有可能的56位密钥，即DES(k,m)等于DES(k',m)的概率
over all 56-bit keys, of the probability that DES(k,m) is equal to DES(k-prime, m).
好吧？那我们问，给定密钥k'
OK? So we're asking, basically, what is this probability, for a fixed key k-prime,
它和密钥k在明文分组m处碰撞的概率多大？想一想
that it happens to collide with the key k at the message m? Well, let's think about this for a second.
我们固定这个值，设想它是某个值
Let's fix this value, let's suppose it's some fixed value. And then we're asking,
然后在点m处，一个随机置换Pi(k')
how likely is it that a random permutation, pi k-prime, at the point m,
正好和密钥k在点m处的输出相同的可能性有多大？
happens to produce exactly the same output as the key k at the point m?
这不难回答，事实上，对于一个密钥k'
Well, it's not difficult to answer and see that in fact this is, for a single key k-prime,
这个概率最多是1除以2的64次方，对吧？这个置换有2的64次方个可能的输出
the probability is at most one over 2^64. Right? There are 2^64 possible outputs for the permutation,
结果正好是这个输出的概率是多少？是1除以2的64次方
what's the probability that it lands exactly on this output? well, it's one over 2^64.
我们对所有2的56次方个密钥求和，即两者相乘
And we're summing over all 2^56 keys, so we just multiply the two,
答案是1除以2的8次方，即1除以256，对吧？
we get one over 2^8, which is basically one over 256. OK? So the probability
所以密钥不唯一的概率是1除以256，所有密钥唯一的概率
that the key is not unique is one over 256, therefore the probability that it is unique
就是1减去它，约99.5%，对吧？那么给我一个明文、密文对
is one minus that, which is 99.5%. OK? So already, if you give me one plaintext-ciphertext pair,
密钥是完全确定的，只有一个密钥可以将那个明文
the key is completely determined. There's only one key that will map that plaintext
映射到那个密文。问题是，能找到这个密钥吗？
to that ciphertext, and the question is just, can you find that key?
事实上，如果我有两个明文密文对，给我明文m1和m2
Now it turns out in fact if you give me two pairs, so you give me m1 and m2,
和它们的相应输出c1和c2
and their corresponding outputs, c1 and c2, the probability basically
经过类似分析，密钥唯一的概率基本上是1了
―just do exactly the same analysis, the probability basically becomes one.
只有一个密钥。好，概率非常接近于1
That there's only one such key. OK, essentially, this is very, very, very close to 1,
如果有两个明文密文对，几乎只可能有一个密钥
and basically it says given two pairs, it's very very likely that only one key
可以满足这两对明文、密文的映射。于是
will map this pair of messages to this pair of ciphertexts, and as a result again,
我们的问题是找到这个唯一的密钥。顺带一提，这一点对AES也成立
we can ask, well, find me that unique key. And by the way, the same is true for AES,
如果你看AES-128，给定两个明文密文对
if you look at AES-128, again, just given two input-output pairs,
以很高的概率只有一个密钥
there's going to be only one key with very high probability. So essentially now
现在我们问的是穷举密钥的问题了，给两个明文密文对，问大家
we can ask this exhaustive search problem, I give you two or three pairs, and I ask you,
帮我找到密钥，该怎么办？可以穷举密钥
well, find me the key. So how are you going to do it? Well, you're going to do it by exhaustive search,
尝试所有可能的密钥，逐一去试，直到找到一个
essentially by trying all possible keys, one by one, until you find the right one.
这就是有名的DES挑战。我解释一下DES挑战的工作过程
So this is what's known as the DES challenge. So let me explain how the DES challenge worked.
这个挑战由RSA公司发起，他们是这样做的
The challenge was issued by a company called RSA, and what they did is basically,
他们公布了一些密文，但有三个密文是知道明文的
they published a number of ciphertexts, but three of the ciphertexts had known plaintexts.
特别地，他们取这里的明文：未知信息是，冒号
So in particular, what they did is they took the message here: The unknown message is, colon,
大家可以看到他们把它分成了若干分组。大家看
and you can see they broke it up into blocks. If you look at these, these are basically
这些是8字节的分组。8字节是64位，所以每个是64位
eight-byte blocks. Eight bytes, as you know, is 64 bits, right, so each of these is 64 bits.
他们使用一个密钥来加密它们。他们使用同一把密钥
And then they encrypted them using a secret key. They encrypted them all using the same
加密三个明文，获得三个密文，这就给我们三组明文密文对
secret key to get three ciphertexts. So this gives us three plaintext-ciphertext pairs,
他们还给我们一组其他密文，c4, c5, c6
and then they gave us a whole bunch of other ciphertexts, you know, c4, c5, c6,
挑战就是，解密这些密文
and the challenge was, decrypt these guys using the key that you found
使用通过穷举法从三组明文密文对上获得的密钥
from an exhaustive search over the first three pairs that you were given.
好，这就叫做DES挑战，我告诉大家花了多长时间
OK. So that was called the DES challenge, and let me tell you a little bit
解决了这个挑战。有趣的是，1997年，使用因特网
about how long it took to solve it. So interestingly, in 1997, using an Internet search,
使用分布式网络，他们可以通过搜索密钥空间
using distributed net, basically, they were able to search through enough of the keyspace
在三个月内找到正确密钥。密钥空间大小是2的56次方
to find the correct key in about three months. You realize the keyspace has size 2^56,
平均下来需要搜索密钥空间的一半才能找到密钥
but on average you only have to search through half the keyspace to find the key,
花了三个月。然后奇迹发生了
and so it took them three months. Then, kind of a miraculous thing happened.
EFF和Paul Kocher合作，构建了一个特殊硬件来破解DES
The EFF actually contracted Paul Kocher to build special-purpose hardware to break DES.
(EFF:电子前沿基金会)
这个机器叫Deep Crack，造价25万美元
This was a machine called Deep Crack. It cost about 250,000 dollars, and it broke
它只用三天就破解了下一个DES挑战。顺便一说，有趣的是
the next DES challenge in only three days. Interestingly, by the way, RSA said that
RSA曾说过为每个DES挑战的解决者支付一万美元
they would pay ten thousand dollars for each solution of a challenge, so you can see
所以这就太不经济了。他们花了25万，解决了挑战却只能获得一万
that this is not quite economical. They spent 250K, they got ten thousand dollars
1999年又有件大事
for solving the challenge. The next thing that happened is in 1999,
RSA发布了另一个挑战，他们说，要用之前的解决方案所花的一半的时间
RSA issued another challenge, and they said, well, I'm gonna solve it in half the time
来解决这个挑战，同时使用Deep Crack和因特网搜索
of the previous solution, and so using both Deep Crack and the Internet search together,
这次他们用了22小时破解了DES
they were able to break DES in 22 hours.
所以至少可以说，DES已死
So the bottom line here is, essentially, DES is completely dead.
如果你忘了密钥，或者丢了，不用着急
Essentially, if you forget, or you lose your DES 56-bit key, don't worry―
只需22小时，你就可以找回密钥，事实上任何人都可以
within 22 hours, you can actually recover it and in fact, anyone can recover it, and so
所以DES已死，不再是安全的。后来又有补刀的
DES essentially is dead and no longer secure. And just kind of a final nail in the coffin,
随着硬件技术的提升，另一个项目叫做COPACABANA，使用了FPGA
as hardware technology improved, there was another project called COPACABANA that used FPGAs,
已下架的FPGA，只需120个，只花一万美元
just off-the-shelf FPGAs, only 120 FPGAs. It only cost 10,000 dollars. And they were able to break,
他们用穷举法在7天内就可以破解DES。非常便宜的硬件，已下架的
to do an exhaustive key search in about seven days. So very, very cheap hardware, just off the shelf,
可以很快就破解DES。所以这里的教训是
you can break DES already very quickly. So the lesson from all this is essentially,
56位密码已经死透了。问题是我们怎么办？
56-bit ciphers are totally, totally dead. And so the question is what to do.
人们很喜欢DES，到处都在用，有许多应用
People really liked DES, it was deployed in a lot of places, there were a lot of implementations,
有许多硬件支持DES，我们怎么办？
there was a lot of hardware support for it, so the question was what to do.
我们想到的第一件事是，也许我们可以就用DES
And so the first thing that came to mind is, well maybe we can take DES
人为地扩充它的密钥空间大小，来抵抗这种穷举攻击
and we can kind of artificially expand the key size, so we strengthen it against
这第一个想法
this exhaustive search attack. And the first idea that comes to mind is basically,
就是多运行这个分组密码几次，就得到了3DES
well, let's iterate the block cipher a couple of times. And this is what's called Triple DES.
3DES也是个一般的分组密码，它是这样工作的
So Triple DES is a general construction. Basically it says the following.
假如给我一个分组密码E，它有密钥空间K
Suppose you gave me a block cipher E. So here, it has a keyspace K,
有明文空间M，当然还有密文空间M
it has a message space M, and an output space of course M as well.
我们定义三重加密，使用三个密钥，如下定义
Let's define the triple construction, which now uses three keys, and it's defined as follows,
三重加密使用三个独立的密钥
basically, here, the triple construction uses three independent keys, encrypts the same
和以前一样加密明文分组，它先使用密钥k3
message block as before, and what it does is, it will encrpyt using the key k3,
然后用密钥k2解密，然后再用密钥k1加密
then it will decrypt using the key k2, then it will encrypt again using the key k1.
所以一共3次，使用独立的密钥
OK so basically encrpyting three times, using three independent keys.
大家可能有疑问，为什么是加密、解密、加密，而不全是加密呢？
You might be wondering, why is it doing E, D, E, why not just do E, E, E?
我们为什么中间要有个解密呢？这只是一个技巧
Why do we have to have a D in the middle? Well, that's just for, uh, kind of a hack.
如果三密钥相等，k1=k2=k3呢？
You notice what happens if you set up k1 equals k2 equals k3? What happens if all three keys
一个加密和一个解密会抵消
are the same? Well, basically, what will happen is, one E and one D would cancel,
你就可以使用正常的DES了。这仅仅是个技巧
and you would just get normal DES out. So it's just a hack so that if you have a hardware implementation
如果你用硬件实现3DES的话，你可以将三个密钥设成一样，这样就是用硬件
of Triple DES, you can set all three keys to be the same, and you'll get a hardware implementation
实现单个DES了。当然速度比单个DES要慢2倍
of single DES. Of course it'll be three times as slow as a regular implementation of single DES,
不过也算是种选择。好，3DES的密钥空间大小
but nevertheless, it's still an option. OK, so for Triple DES now we get a key size
是3乘以56，168位。168位对于穷举攻击要花的时间太长了
that's 3 times 56, which is 168 bits; this is, 168 bits is way too long to do an exhaustive search on.
2的168次方的时间，就算地球上所有机器一起工作10年
That will take time 2^168, which is more than all the machines on earth working for ten years
也是不能破解的。不幸的是，其速度比DES当然要慢两倍
would be able to do. Unfortunately, of course, the cipher is three times slower than DES.
这是3DES的一个问题。我想提一下
So this is a real problem with Triple DES. Now I want to mention that in fact you might think
大家可能认为3DES的安全性是2的168次方的，
但事实上，有一个简单的攻击，只需2的118次方
Triple DES has security 2^168, but in fact, there is a simple attack that runs in time 2^118,
我想为大家展示这个攻击是怎么工作的，好吧？
但尽管如此，2的118次方依然是足够大的
and I want to show you how that attack works. OK? So― but in fact 2^118 is still a large number.
事实上，任何大于2的90次方的都可被认为是充分安全的
In fact, anything that's, kind of, bigger than 2^90 is considered sufficiently secure.
2的118次方被认为是对穷举攻击充分安全的
2^118 is definitely sufficiently secure against exhaustive search,
被认为是个足够高的安全级别了
and generally is considered a high enough level of security.
当然3DES比DES慢出2倍。问题是
So clearly Triple DES is three times as slow as DES. So the question is,
为什么要重复加密3次？两次为什么不行？
why did they repeat the cipher three times? Why not repeat the cipher just two times,
特别地，双重DES有什么错？
or in particular, the question is, what's wrong with double DES?
这里我们有双重DES。可以看到它只使用2个密钥
So here we have double DES. Basically you see it uses only two keys, and it uses only
只使用两次加密，所以比DES要慢一倍
two applications of the block cipher, and as a result it's only going to be twice as slow as DES,
不是慢两倍。双重DES的密钥长度是2乘以56，112位
not three times as slow as DES. Well, the key length for double DES is 2 times 56, which is
事实上对112位密钥空间的穷举搜索也需太多时间
112 bits, and in fact doing exhaustive search on a space of 112 bits is too much.
2的112次方如此之大，穷举攻击不适用
2^112 is too big of a number to do exhaustive search over such a large space.
问题是，双重DES有什么错？
So the question is, what's wrong with this construction. Well, it turns out
事实上这个加密机制一点都不安全，我想给出一个攻击
this construction is completely insecure, and I want to show you an attack.
我有一组输入m1到m10，有对应的输出
So, suppose I'm given a bunch of inputs, say m1 to m10, and I'm given the corresponding outputs
c1到c10。我的目的是找到这两个密钥k1和k2
c1 to c10. What's my goal? Well, my goal is basically to find keys, you know, a pair of keys k1, k2,
如果我用这些密钥加密明文M，换句话说如果我加密
such that if I encrypt the message M using these keys, in other words if I do this encryption,
使用双重DES，那么我就得到给我的这些密文向量
this double DES encryption, then I get the ciphertext vector that was given to me.
好，我们的目标是解决这个问题。再看一会这个方程
OK, so our goal is to solve this equation here. Now you stare at this equation a little bit,
我们发现，等会，我可以把它改写成一个有趣的形式
and you realize, hey wait a minute, I can rewrite it in kind of an interesting way;
我可以应用解密算法，得到的结果是，我要找的
I can apply the decryption algorithm, and then what I'll get is that I'm really looking for
密钥k1和k2，满足这个方程。我只是把应用密钥k1的解密算法
keys k1, k2 that satisfy this equation here, where basically all I did is I applied
应用在等式的两边。好，只要看到类似的等式
the decryption algorithm using k1 to both sides. OK, now whenever you see an equation like this,
我们把变量分成了两边
what just happened here is that we separated our variables into two sides,
出现在方程两边的变量，通常意味着
the variables now appear on independent sides of the equation, and that usually means
存在一个比穷举更快的攻击，事实上这个攻击叫做
that there is a faster attack than exhaustive search, and in fact this attack is called
中间相遇攻击，就是针对加密机制里的这个弱点的
a meet-in-the-middle attack, where really the meet-in-the-middle is going to somehow
好，那我们试试
attack this particular point in the construction. OK, so we're going to try and find a key
去找到一个密钥把m映射到某个特定值，把c也映射到同样值
that maps m to a particular value here, and maps c to the same value.
好，我告诉大家这个攻击怎么工作。第一件事
OK, so let me show you how the attack works. So the first thing we're going to do is
我们创建一张表。我腾出些地方
we're going to build a table. Here, let me clear up some space here.
第一步是构建一张表，存放所有可能的k2
The first step is to build a table that for all possible values of k2,
用于加密m，好，我们有这表
encrypts m under that value. OK, so here we have this table, so you notice
注意到一共2的56次方个DES密钥，好，该表有2的56次方项
these are all 2^56 single DES keys, OK, so the table has 2^56 entries,
对于每一项，我们用对应密钥加密m
and what we do is basically, for each entry, we compute the encryption of m
所以这是用全0密钥加密m的结果
under the appropriate key. So this is the encryption of m under the all-zero key,
用密钥1加密m的结果，最底下是用全1密钥加密m的结果
the encryption of m under the one key, and at the bottom, we have the encryption of m
好，一共2的56次方项，我们根据第二列对这张表进行排序
under the all-one key. OK, so there are 2^56 entries, and we sort this table based on the second column.
目前还不错，建这张表需要花时间2的56次方
OK, so far, so good. So by the way this takes time―to build this table takes time 2^56,
排序的话需要n log n的时间，所以是2^56 乘以 log 2^56
and I guess we also want to sort, sorting takes n log n time, so it's 2^56 times log 2^56. OK.
好，现在我们有了这个表，我们还要从正向，考虑所有可能密钥k1
So now that we have this table, we've essentially built all possible values
再建一个类似这样的表
in the forward direction for this point.
然后我们要做的就是中间相遇攻击
Now what we're going to do is this meet-in-the-middle attack,
我们现在试图从相反方向，用所有可能的密钥k
where now we try to go in the reverse direction with all possible keys k.
我们用所有可能的密钥k1来解密c
Essentially we compute the decryption of c under all possible keys k1.
好，这样对每个可能的解密，记住这张表存放着所有可能的中间值
OK, so now for each potential decryption, remember the table holds all possible values
然后对每个可能的解密，我们检查发现，这个解密结果
in the midpoint, so then for each possible decrpytion, we check, hey, is the decryption in the table,
是否在表中第2列里？如果在，就说明我们找到了配对
in the second column in the table? If it is in the table, then aha, we found the match,
然后呢？我们找到了一对配对的密钥
and then what do we know? We know that essentially, well, we found the match, so we know that
用k1解密正好和表中这一项吻合
say for example a decryption using a particular key k1 happened to match this entry in the table,
k2或更一般的ki，我们知道用ki加密m的结果
say, k2 or more generally ki, then we know that the encryption of m under ki
等于用k解密c的结果。好，我们构建了这个中间相遇攻击
is equal to the decryption of c under k. OK, so we kind of build this meet-in-the-middle,
两边，用ki加密m，和用k解密c
where the two sides, you know, the encryption of m under ki and the decryption of c under k,
发生碰撞了。如果碰撞了，我们知道事实上这对(ki,k)
collided, but if they collided, then we know that in fact this pair, ki and k, is equal to
就等于我们要找的密钥对，也就解决了我们的挑战
the pair that we're looking for. And so we've just solved our challenge.
现在我们看看这个攻击的运行时间是多少？首先需要建表
So now let's look at what's the running time of this? Well, we had to build a table,
然后排序，然后对所有可能的解密，还需要查找表
and sort it, and then for all possible decryptions, we had to do a search through the table.
有2的56次方个可能的解密，每个在排好序的表里
二分查找需要log(2^56)的时间
So there were 2^56 possible decryptions, each search in a sorted table takes log(2^56) time,
最后算出来是2的63次方，比2的112次方小得多
if you just work it out this turns out to be 2^63, which is way, way, way, way, way smaller
好，这是一个很严重的攻击，是可适用的
than 2^112. OK, so this is a serious attack, it's probably doable today, that runs in a total time
用时2的63次方，基本上和DES的穷举攻击耗时差不多
of 2^63, which is about the same time as the exhaustive search attack on DES.
所以，双重DES并没有解决穷举攻击的问题
So really, double DES really didn't solve the exhaustive search problem,
因为有中间相遇攻击，可以用与DES穷举差不多的时间
because, well, there's an attack on it that runs in about the same time
就能破解双重DES。可能有人会抱怨
as exhaustive search on single DES. Now someone might complain
在这个攻击算法里，我们需要存放如此大的表
that in fact this algorithm, well, we have to store this big table,
它会占据大量空间。确实如此
so it takes up a lot of space, but you know, so be it. Nevertheless, the running time
不过，运行时间还是很短的，比2的112次方小得多
is still quite small or significantly smaller than 2^112.
注意到，这个攻击也可应用于3DES
Now you notice, by the way, this same attack applies to Triple DES.
你需要在这里实现中间相遇攻击
What you would do is you would implement the meet-in-the-middle attack against this point,
你需要构建一个大小为2的56次方的表，存放所有m的加密
you would build a table of size 2^56 of all possible encryptions of m,
然后试图用2的112次方个可能的密钥去解密密文，直到发现碰撞
and then you would try to decrypt with all 2^112 keys until you find a collision,
当你发现碰撞时，你就找到了k1，k2和k3
and when you find a collision, you have basically found k1, k2, k3.
好，即使是3DES，也有攻击只搜索了2的112次方个可能密钥
OK, so even Triple DES has an attack that basically explores only 2^112 possible keys.
但2的112次方是足够大的数，所以3DES事实上，到目前为止
But 2^112 is a large enough number, so Triple DES in fact, as far as we know,
是足够安全的。应当提一下，3DES实际上是NIST标准
is sufficiently secure. I should mention that Triple DES is actually a NIST standard,
所以3DES实际上应用广泛，而DES不应再被使用了
and so Triple DES is actually used quite a bit, and in fact DES should never ever ever be used,
如果出于某些原因，你一定要用DES的某种变体，用3DES，别用DES
if for some reason you're forced to use some version of DES, use Triple DES, not DES.
好，我想再提一个增强DES抵抗穷举攻击能力的方法
OK, I want to mention one more method for strengthening DES against exhaustive search attacks.
这个方法没有被NIST标准化，因为它不能抵抗
This method actually is not standardized by NIST, because it doesn't defend against
针对DES更为复杂的攻击，不过如果只考虑穷举攻击
more subtle attacks on DES, but nevertheless if all you're worried about is exhaustive search,
又不想承担3DES的性能开销，这就是个有趣的想法
and you don't want to pay the performance penalties of Triple DES, then this is an interesting idea.
我来告诉大家它是怎么工作的。设E为一个n位字符串上的分组密码
So let me show you how it works. So let E be a block cipher that operates on n-bit blocks.
我们定义EX机制，对于DES就是DESX，以如下方式
We're going to define the EX construction, and for DES we're going to get DESX, to be the following.
我们使用密钥k1,k2,k3，然后在加密前，用k3异或明文分组
So we use three keys, k1, k2, k3, and then basically before encrpytion, we XOR with k3,
然后用k2加密明文，然后将加密结果异或k1，完事
then we encrypt using k2, and then after encryption we XOR with k1. That's it.
这就是整个过程。注意到它并没有拖慢分组密码太多
That's the whole construction. So basically, you'll notice it doesn't slow the block cipher much,
因为多的只是附加的两个异或操作，很快的
because all we did is we applied the cipher plus two additional XORs, which are super fast.
密钥长度，事实上，这两个密钥和明文分组一样长
The key length for this is in fact, well, we got two keys that are as long as the block size,
另一个密钥和原DES密钥长度一致，所以总共是184位
and we got one key that's as long as the key size, so the total is 184 bits.
实际上目前针对DESX的最好攻击需要时间2的120次方
Now, it turns out actually the best attack that's known is actually an attack that takes time 2^120,
这个例子挺不错的。对EX的通用攻击，会花掉时间相当于穷举
and this is actually fairly simple. So it's a generic attack on EX, it will always take time basically
分组长度加密钥长度的可能密钥，这个留为简单家庭作业
block size plus the key size, and it's a simple homework problem
(提示：类似于中间相遇攻击)
大家想想为什么？我想这是个很好的练习
for you to try to figure out this attack. I think this is a good exercise.
好，事实上一些分析显示对这种类型的加密
OK, in fact there is some analysis to show that there is no exhaustive search attack
没有穷举攻击，所以它抵抗穷举攻击很有效
on this type of construction, so it's a fine construction against exhaustive search,
但还有一些更复杂的针对DES的攻击，我们留到下一节
but there are more subtle attacks on DES that we'll talk about in the next segment,
届时这种密码机制就不行了
that basically this construction will not prevent.
我还想指出一点，很不幸地，我在很多产品中发现了这个错误
One thing that I want to point out, unfortunately I found this mistake in a number of products,
那就是决定在外面进行异或，或是在里面
is if you just decide to XOR on the outside, or if you just decide to XOR on the inside,
而不是像DESX那样是在两边
as opposed to XOR-ing on both sides, which is what DESX does,
注意到DESX在里面和外面都有异或
you notice DESX XORs both on the outside and on the inside,
如果只做一个，那么这个密码机制将一点都不安全
If you just do one of them, then basically this construction does nothing
它对穷举攻击依然是脆弱的
to secure your cipher. It'll still be as vulnerable to exhaustive search
和原先的分组密码E一样脆。好，这又是一道练习
as the original block cipher E. OK, so this is another homework problem,
(提示：类似于中间相遇攻击)
将是我们练习的一部分，好
and actually you'll see that as part of our homeworks. OK.
那么这就讲完了穷举攻击
So this basically concludes our discussion of exhaustive search attacks,
下面我们讨论针对DES的更为复杂的攻击
and next we'll talk about more sophisticated attacks on DES.